Good evening. Shout out to everybody out there. Shout out to the Global Summit Flotilla, the brave folks that are at sea right now being attacked by these Israeli ships with skunk water and, you know, attempting to just bring them down.
But they continue to share with us where they're at, what they're doing. And we got to continue to keep them lifted.
So if you're wondering what the title of this is, tonight begins a series that I'll be doing up until November 8th when I have the book launch and live stream performance of my one woman show, What Would the Ancestors Say?
And I've been developing this for a year. And we are in a time where we need to really be asking ourselves in real ways, what would our ancestors say about where we are and what ancestors would we be for those moving forward?
And, you know, we just lost Assata Shakur, who becomes an ancestor to all of us.
And thus, we have to continue to carry forth the work that they're doing.
So I want to invite folks to be able to come on screen and talk to me about what about what their ancestors would say about where we are now.
So, and I'm not sure why this person is telling me what the black community should do.
I do not control what the black community does.
So, that's not like my, the black community needs to stop using Mexican as an insult.
That would be like me saying Mexicans need to stop stealing jobs from the black community, which I would not say, because that sounds crazy.
Because one, that's not even a thing.
And nonetheless, it is a thing that is said.
So, and I am Mickey.
That's not what I'm saying either.
We're not having black talk.
Ancestors are those who have come before all of us.
All of my ancestors are not black.
Okay?
My ancestors that I speak to and that speak to me and that lift me up and that build me up are those who are for liberation and who have been for liberation and who are connected to the indigenous.
That is what ancestry is.
So, if you would like to come on and talk about how you feel your ancestors would respond to where we are now, I invite you to come on.
So, I see two people here that have requested to join.
I'm going to wait for a couple more options.
And the idea is for us to be in shared space and considering of what is an ancestor?
Who do we consider to be our ancestors?
How do we connect to their wisdom?
I am a very big believer that that disconnect is a big reason we are where we are.
I was outside as well.
So, I want to hear from you all and give you all the space to speak and share your insights on your ancestry.
So, I'm not.
So, and this again is in response to my book, What Would the Ancestors Say?
which is the published text of my one-woman show by the same name that I will be performing on live stream after a year of developing it.
And I'll be performing it on November 8th.
So, ask to come on and then be surprised when you are, when you are accepted.
Because that's the thing y'all love to do.
Thank you.
One, say Chloe and Bridget.
But say it.
Tammy, did you know that you requested to come on?
I don't think I realized that.
Sorry.
I thought I just meant like, and of course my kids are in the background.
So, all right.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
You see what I'm saying?
See what I mean?
So, again, if you would like to come on to speak about what you feel your ancestors would do.
Or how you feel your ancestors would feel about where we are.
But see though, you about to get blocked.
Because I don't even know what the hell you're talking about right now.
The black community don't even be accepting me.
So, what are we even talking about?
Go talk to one of these other blacks about that.
Did you do this on purpose?
I did do this on purpose.
Okay.
I'm Nathaniel Whitaker.
I am a descendant on my father's side.
My great-grandfather, whose middle name, his first name is my middle name, Junius Whitaker.
And he was a sharecropper from Scotland at North Carolina.
And what's funny is how our family got to Virginia was because his brother, Ananias, actually fought a landowner and had to escape on a train to Virginia.
So, that's how, like, my family lineage got to Virginia.
But, I don't know.
I think that with what's going on today, what would my ancestors say about what's happening?
It's to keep being resilient.
You know, my great-grandfather, he ended up, when he moved to Virginia, he moved into this community, Lambert's Point, built a two-story home, raised a family of nine children.
And, you know, I'm just sitting here, you know, thinking, you know, with all that's going on in the world and how overwhelmed I am.
By the way, I'm a Morehouse alum.
My background is in Africana studies, so I love the work that you're doing.
And currently working on my master's, but just been overwhelmed lately and kind of been feeling that sense of hopelessness in a way, but also realizing what our ancestors went through.
I mean, for my great-grandfather to be a sharecropper, you know, and to build a home and to raise a family in the midst of all of, I mean, this is the 30s, like the Great Depression.
Right.
You know, it's like, so, and we have way more resources and power, you know, than they had, you know?
And how do we use that and strategize and come together as a community to truly get over this hurdle, you know?
It's so many ways, but, you know, like, again, I appreciate this conversation, but, yeah, I just had to share that, you know,
about my great-grandfather, and my mind is kind of all over the place, so causing my points to be all over the place, but I just wanted to share that, you know,
it's like the government shutdown.
It's just too much going on, but I just actually got out of class, so that's why I'm in the car.
What was the class?
I'm actually taking a leadership.
It's called Game Changers Leadership, and so I'm currently at SCAD Atlanta working on my Master's of Business Innovation.
And then I'll be moving on to my PhD in African American Studies, but I'm going into the theme park industry and looking to bring Black culture into how we redesign theme parks.
And so I'm building my startup currently right now, and I have a game coming out in 2027.
And so it's within gaming and theme park design and bringing Black culture into that and how we could connect culture to fun and immersive experience and everything like that.
So, yeah.
Where do you – when you talk about Black culture, where does it begin and end for you?
So Black culture starts in Africa, right?
So I'm looking at Black culture as a diaspora, so, you know, incorporating every aspect of Black culture.
So, like, when we think, like, the word Afro, right, means all, like, parts of the diaspora.
So that's, you know, Caribbean, African, African American, even South America.
Afro-Latina.
Then also you have African people in, you know, the aging continent, right?
So it's, like, incorporating all of these elements of Black culture from, you know, from the diaspora to create fun cultural imagination.
I study Afrofuturism at Morehouse.
That was, like, my thesis base, so, like, a lot of that.
So, yeah.
So it's a lot of moving elements.
But to answer your question, yes, I start at Africa because, you know, that's where our roots are from and everything.
So I'm not of the belief that Black culture is just limited to Black American culture.
You know, it includes all, you know, types of culture.
So, yeah.
I know one of the things that's been bugging me lately is the thought of, well, the contextualizing of Black culture, like, solely in what we create.
In terms of, like, our innovation, but not in our, but not thinking about Black culture also within our social context, right?
And our movements, our leadership.
And our leadership beyond just trying to infiltrate white spaces, right?
Right.
Like, that there's been, like, a very, like, effective disassociation of the, like, the necessary political context of being Black.
Like, um, to where it's become just, like, dances.
Mm-hmm.
You know, like, people think about Black culture and they're, like, thinking of, like, the Cosby Show.
Yeah.
The Fresh Prince of L.A.
And that's why the startup that I'm building is moving into the theme park industry because I think that it's a very underrepresented lane of entertainment that, one, you know, lacks Black representation, but not just Black representation in terms of the interface of it, but I'm talking about the innovation of theme parks, right?
And so, um, because, you know, like, we, we have, like, TV and film, like, you know, though there can be better diversity and things like that, we have that, like, we have that lot.
We have music lot.
But when you think of Black culture, you're not thinking of a theme park, right?
And so, and then even our relationships, the history and the historical context with Black people and an amusement, like, of how we were used as exhibitions.
I want to kind of have a reclamation of that, of, like, no, we're not the, just the exhibition that, you know, you just pat on and touch, like, we're animals, but we're the drivers of innovation in this space.
And we have stories that, plenty of stories, literature, aesthetics, culture to build these worlds off of.
Um, so, yeah, I definitely agree with you on that.
And actually, to your point about, you know, different cultures and, um, coming together, you know, I study Marcus Garvey a lot in what he did, you know, with how he organized, like, across the diaspora, how powerful that was.
Like, we're, I want us to, like, we're more, we're more together than we are separate.
Like, this whole diaspora wars and stuff, like, it's just, we need to come together and truly build our own spaces, you know, and stop looking for white validation to, to validate us.
You know, we need to build these spaces amongst ourselves.
So, you know, I'm at SCAD Atlanta right now, building this startup, and, um, I'll be building this within my PhD program, whatever PhD program I get into.
But I'm based in Atlanta, um, by the way, Atlanta, Georgia.
So, yep.
Well, I just wanted, before, before we go, I just want to challenge you to consider how you can create this and have it exist in a socialist context.
Okay.
All right.
Yeah, and I would, like, and honestly, I don't, like, talk to you more, because, like, you know, like I said, I follow your work, and.
I don't say this all the time.
I want to talk to you more.
Y'all want to talk to you more.
No, but you're serious.
I'm serious because I'm a scholar myself.
So, it's like, you know, the, the, the conversation that you have and everything like that, you know, it's, it's, it's right up my alley.
And, um, you know, so, like, whatever that looks like, right?
Um.
You're talking to me right now.
You got to talk to me right now.
I do, right.
Exactly.
You know, so this is, like, how, I, that's something.
Don't get greedy.
You, you got access to me right now.
Not many people can say that.
So.
Right.
You know what I'm saying?
So, I just, but I want, I, I, I, I'm imploring black folks to think beyond how to participate in capitalism.
And to think beyond how their innovation becomes a tool of capitalism.
It doesn't mean you stop innovating.
It doesn't mean you stop creating.
But it does challenge us to think about how our innovation and creation is more serving to our communities, to our goals of, um, preservation, right?
Right.
Other than, uh, because once you understand that capitalism is the, has been the seed of oppression, you can't cognizantly continue to feed it.
Mm-hmm.
And that is the challenge I give to everybody who wants to, beyond black people.
Everybody who wants to see a world where there is actual abundance that is shared versus that is lied, you know, because we get lied to that there is an abundance.
There is abundance.
Like, there is enough water.
There's enough food.
There's enough land.
All of this exists.
Right.
Um, and so, I, I encourage, especially folks like yourself who are in the space of scholarship, who are in the space of learning, to, to add that extra layer of considering in your innovation.
Got you.
Okay.
That sounds good.
I mean, this was a potent combo.
Right.
No, it's definitely, this is like a Zoom call.
Yes, Marble Class, you can speak about any ancestors.
These are not just black ancestors.
I don't think all my ancestors are black.
How?
Oh, yeah.
No, I had a French ancestor.
Listen, um, apparently I am a descendant of Robert E. Lee.
Oh, God.
I like to think that I'm flipping that, you know, because they, they was doing their own revolution.
People really do not want to admit that revolutions are not always positive, but it's a fact.
Yeah.
I mean, the American revolution was a positive.
I said that Trump is a revolutionary the other day, and they tried to spin it and use it as clickbait, but it's like, he's literally moving outside the lines with a full force behind him and pushing an agenda forward that removes the current one that is in place.
That would technically be the book definition of a revolution, literally.
So, in this context, the counter-revolution is to do the opposite, which is to think in terms of how do we get the labor practices and the labor, the powers of labor to the people.
It is how do we, how do we, how do we, how do we not have a world of 10 billionaires?
Mm-hmm.
Like, why, why do 36 people own 1%, I mean, own 80% of the wealth in the world?
That's crazy.
Yeah, it is.
And then, like, battling to try to get there, that don't make no damn sense.
Yeah, it's a mess.
And I appreciate, you know, the work that you're doing.
You know, I've been following you for quite a while and listening to you.
And honestly, like, your work has grown on me.
You know, like, I have had to challenge myself to deconstruct a lot of, you know, a lot of thoughts, right?
And I'm kind of in that phase right now of deconstructing.
Because, like, you know, they're, like, early on, like, you know, I was like, hmm, okay, I got to, I got to try to understand what you're saying here.
But once you deconstruct and keep learning and reading, like, it just starts to naturally click and those rose-colored glasses come off, right?
So.
Well, the other thing, too, is removing ego.
If all of us just continue to, like, make a practice of removing ego, you know, we gain so much, right?
It doesn't mean that you have to accept bullshit.
It doesn't mean that you have to accept anything that's told to you as true.
But it allows you to be curious.
Yeah.
That's one of our greatest gifts, you know, being curious.
So I'm going to bring somebody else up.
But thank you so much for sharing what your ancestors would say.
It was nice meeting you.
It's good luck with everything.
I want to be on a Kente cloth roller coaster in 10 years, okay?
Look, I got you.
I got y'all.
Y'all just stay tuned.
Follow me.
I have a game coming out in summer 2027.
So just stay tuned for everything.
All right.
Thank you.
Love it.
All right.
Bye.
Hey, me, Jay Walker.
So we are here right now for tonight's edition of What Would Your Ancestors Say?
And this is in accordance with the live stream and book release of my show, What Would the Ancestors Say?
I have written it down so that you all are able to hold it, to read it, to highlight it, to talk about it amongst your friends, your peoples, because it is imperative that we not only put these thoughts and this text and these visions out into the world, but that we actually record it, right?
The written word ends up being so integral to our ability to keep these stories going.
So make sure to sign up for my newsletter.
The link is in bio so that you can get the link for my book release and my live stream of What Would the Ancestors Say?
Which is happening on November 8th, all right?
All right.
So let's bring somebody else up.
And remember, when I ask what would your ancestors say, I'm not speaking just about black people.
All of us have ancestors.
You know, you white folks, what would your ancestors say about where we are?
Be honest with us and yourself.
All right?
So let's see who else is up here.
Oh, now we got all these folks coming up in here.
All right.
Let's see.
Um, let's see.
Okay.
So again, stop asking to come up.
And then when I bring you up, declining.
Please stop doing that.
It wastes everybody's time.
And it's also annoying.
It's annoying.
Um, let's see if this person is going to come up.
We don't know, but we going to find out.
No?
Got it.
All right.
Let's find somebody else.
I don't know.
I'm not from Chicago.
Hi.
Hello.
Are you purposely only showing your partner?
My bad.
Is this so funny?
I was literally watching your Jubilee episode and I saw you were on live.
You are so patient and so kind with these people.
I just want to say that.
And then John to the actual topic.
Thank you so much.
The Global Simifotilla has joined and I'm, I'm, there's been a lot going on with them.
So shout out to the people on the Global Simifotilla who have risked their lives, risked their safety
ability to continue to force the issue of creating a humanitarian corridor to the people of Hessa.
We all know that they are in a absolute, like legitimate journey of humanism.
And we have to lift up their, lift up our voices in support of them.
So big up to the Global Sumifotilla.
So what is your name, lovely?
My name is Mira.
Hello, Mira.
Hi.
So welcome to tonight's edition of What Would Your Ancestors Say?
Yeah.
So what would your, well, who are your ancestors?
What do you, who do you consider to be your ancestors?
And what would they say about the world we're in now?
Um, first of all, I think that's such an interesting question.
And I just want to say English is not my first language.
So great to me.
Um, so on my mother's side, we're Inu, so indigenous.
I'm in Canada right now, in Quebec.
Oh, so French is your first language.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay.
Oui, oui.
Parle-tu français?
Petit peu, petit peu, petit peu.
That's good.
And on my dad's side, so white, um, descendant from Europe.
Okay.
And I guess the way, and that's so interesting, you're starting this conversation in that week
because yesterday was like the, the day that the government chose to like recognize what
happened with the residential school.
Um, and I guess what would my answer say is that we'll still hear, you know, I think that's
the most, I'm sorry, I'm getting emotional.
Take your time.
We survived.
And we'll still hear.
We're surviving.
Well, yeah, exactly.
My bad.
Um, and you know.
So, uh, so, you know, like for those who don't know the residential schools in Canada, which
existed until 1996.
And I learned yesterday that they still take, um, indigenous children away from their communities
and their parents.
Uh, these schools were created and they, they have school, similar schools in the United
States were created to assimilate children out of their indigenous practices and traditions.
Uh, they would separate the boys and girls.
They wouldn't allow them to speak their native languages.
They would beat them, um, into basically the submission of being a land Canadian.
Yeah.
To kill the Indian.
And in their words, that's, that's, that's what, that's what the purpose was, you know?
Um, and the enter, enter generational trauma that this left in all of us is, is very real,
you know?
Like I try to reconnect with my culture, you know, but my grandma wasn't allowed to speak
the language to practice any of like the traditional, um, practices, you know, and ceremony and stuff
like that.
So it's really hard for us to like reconnect to something that I don't want to say that's
lost.
Cause like, it's still there, you know, but, but it's covered, it's, it's, it's, it's like
you have to dig your way out.
Exactly.
Yeah.
So what would my answer say?
And, you know, I, I'm finishing my master and I think they would be really proud of me,
you know, getting keys in education.
I think that's a big thing, you know?
Mm-hmm.
Congrats.
Yeah.
Thank you.
What made you decide to go get your master's in education?
I think you're muted.
Is she muted?
What happened?
Okay.
My bad.
Sorry.
What was the question?
What made you decide to go get your master's in education?
Honestly, the pressure of like feeling like I'm accomplishing something like, honestly,
that's, that's kind of sad answer, but yeah, the pressure of like feeling like I need a diploma
to be someone when I think about it.
Yeah.
But obviously I'm glad I got education, you know, but that was the, the main reason, honestly.
That's why I got mine.
Yeah.
You know, and then you get older and you're like, you know.
But that's the world we're in, though.
Mm-hmm.
You know, where you, where you end up needing to have these certain credentials in order
to be validated.
Yeah.
Which, you know, I think there is something to be said for study, right?
For having, you know, rigorous study and for committing yourself to research and learning.
And there is a validity to like the degree reflecting that you have made that commitment.
Yeah.
But then when you see these dummies.
You're like, exactly, exactly.
Those dummies.
Oh, God.
This is so good.
So, mm-mm.
Thank you for bringing me on the live.
This is such a privilege to talk to you.
I've been following you for so many years, you know, and watching you mainly in front of
my TV and be like, yeah, let's go.
Yeah.
Thank you so much.
I feel, you know, I feel like I can hear y'all cheering when I'm doing these things.
Yes, I hope you do.
So, I go in these spaces, you know, sparingly.
But when I do, it's because I know that there's folks that are like, I have to go into spaces
like this all the time.
Yeah.
Whether it's in a classroom or at work or dinner with your family where you feel like
it's one against 20.
It's very tough.
And I think, yeah, you have that, like, that thing inside of you that you don't really
care.
Like, you know the purpose and you know your message and that's what's important, you know?
And this is a true inspiration because so many times I felt like I was in these spaces
and I had my truth, you know?
Yep.
And like, it's so hard to like say, okay, I look like a fool, but this is my truth, you
know?
You don't look like a fool, right?
Like, I think that's the reality is that you feel like you're a fool when everybody
else is an idiot, right?
And you're not.
You know, like, sometimes people will say to me, like, everyone can't be wrong.
And I'm like, yes, they can.
Yes.
You know, like, when I was in the entertainment business, people would be like, well, everyone
can't be the problem.
And I'm like, yeah, they are because the business is the problem.
You know, if I join the police force and they're like, well, everybody can't be a bad cop.
Yes.
Because policing is bad.
So, it is very possible that you're in a space that never works because you're vibrationally
unaligned.
Oh, this is so important.
You know?
Yeah.
So, like, so many of us that are in institutions, you know, whether it's medical or school, etc.
You're like, damn, I feel crazy here.
And you have to figure out how to, like, milk the rock.
But don't you think that sometimes, like, you have to pick your battles?
Yes.
In terms of, like, right now, I don't have this energy.
But for me, it's so tough to, like, let it go.
You know?
I don't think you have to let it go.
I think it's almost like what has really, really changed my life is pausing.
It's really letting, um...
Interesting.
Letting myself pause and process.
And so, it's not that I have to let it go.
I just need to shelve it.
You know?
It needs to mature.
It needs to kind of, you know, figure out something else.
And then you decide, like, how do I want to approach this?
And what gets overwhelming is when you feel like you've got to face every battle all at the same time.
You're like, that's some bullshit.
That's whack.
I don't like that.
And you feel like you've got to deal with it all.
And it's like, I'm going to put these over here for now.
I'm going to deal with this one right here.
And, like, when I was in that debate, that was how I had to, like, manage all that coming at me, right?
It's like...
Yeah.
You just said seven ridiculous statements.
Which one?
I can't deal with all seven.
I can see it in your face.
I swear.
Like, I talk with my face a lot.
And you do, too.
And I can literally, like, hear you talk with your face.
You're like, really?
And you don't say anything.
I love it so much.
You know, but that's something I've had to really practice.
It's like, let's just pause and not pull out all the weapons and let them present, you know?
I watch a lot of, like, kung fu movies and, like, fighting movies.
And you'll see so often that the, like, main fighter will let these people just...
And you're like, yeah, tire yourself out.
They come and they're like...
And then they just do a quick...
So, you know, it's...
But it's something that we're not really taught to do.
You know, we're also...
We also have been trained to be so reactive.
And that if you're not kind of, like, responding immediately, then there's a problem.
And if you see interviews that I do, I take my time.
I breathe before I respond.
And, you know, I give myself the opportunity to not get caught up in somebody else's nonsense.
And that's...
But how do you actually do it in the moment?
Like, I get so sorry.
You have to breathe.
It's practice.
You have to really breathe.
And you have to...
This is going to sound really cheesy, but it's like...
Whenever possible, if you can do it, you have to remember, like, oh, I'm here to be love.
Like, that's what I'm here to be.
Yeah.
I'm here to be love.
Now, sometimes I don't got that.
Somebody had me yelling on the phone today.
Okay?
I was yelling on the phone today.
I was like, why are you...
I love it.
Listen, sometimes I don't got it.
But I try my best.
And that's all we really can do is genuinely try our best.
Not just say we're trying our best.
Because some people will be like, I'm trying.
No the fuck you not.
Yeah.
You're just saying that.
But I really do try.
And I got to tell you, practice the pause.
That's the thing.
Take a deep breath.
When the nonsense happens, you just...
So when I...
I talk about this all the time.
When I was on the show, The Real, there would be so much nonsense being said.
And it was a live show.
So it's not like they can edit.
And I had to learn how to not feel like I got a response.
Yeah.
So the tip that I was given is you breathe in what someone's saying.
And then you exhale it back to them.
Interesting.
So you're listening, but you're not internalizing.
So they're yapping and you're like, and they might be like, damn, she's breathing real hard.
But whatever, that's their problem to deal with.
So, you know, I wish you the best.
And, you know, continue on your journey, on your search for connection.
I mean, I think that's a lifelong work.
It's not something that necessarily just happens immediately.
But I think in the quest, so many of us haven't even considered or weren't even able to pursue the quest.
Right.
So that in itself is an act of defiance, of resilience, of resistance.
Yeah.
It's definitely been a journey.
I feel like the shame of like trying to reconnect.
It's so interesting what's happening here.
You know, like we're trying to reconnect, but we have the shame that we don't have the knowledge yet.
But there's a reason why we don't have it.
Yeah.
It's very much internalizing.
It's like that's what they want from you and you can't give them that.
Yeah.
You have to really be on something like, fuck y'all.
I'm love you.
Yeah.
Okay.
Oh, I'm so glad I talked to you.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
And good luck with your masters.
Bon chance.
Au revoir.
Oh, man.
If you're joining us, this is What Would Your Ancestors Say?
And I'll be doing these regularly throughout the next month as I'm preparing for the release of my book by the same title, What Would the Ancestors Say?
And the live stream performance.
Yes.
This is happening on November 8th.
If you want to be one of the first to get the tickets and to get ready, then make sure you sign up for my newsletter at the link in bio.
I'm really excited because I've been spending a year working on this project.
I have never gotten the luxury of working that long to develop something and to get it to where I want it to.
And this is a labor of not love in the sense of like, you know, oh, I made this thing.
It's a labor of love in that I made it for us.
I made it for us as a tool for where we are, right?
And I made it for us as a text that we can lean into and love through in really considering who our ancestors, how our ancestors would think about where we are and what ancestors are we for the future.
And I think that's something that not enough of us ask ourselves, right?
We don't ask ourselves that.
We don't challenge ourselves in that regard.
And thus, we don't show up in the way that we need to to be connected to the work that they did.
Now, Flora, I'm bringing you back up.
Now, remember, your ancestry is your ancestry.
So it's whatever you name it to be.
Hello, Flora.
Hi.
I can't believe I'm talking to you.
You have perfect teeth.
O-M-G.
You just bring the matriarchal energy that I need in my life.
And I'm just there's so many times that last conversation you had about, like, you being the only wrong person in the room.
I just, like, I feel so lonely sometimes.
And then I come and you speak the fire that's in my heart.
You're saying the words that I'm like, I knew that I'm not crazy.
There must be other people who feel this way.
I mean, in these days and times, I think it's so common that this happens, you know.
And eventually, all these people are going to say, oh, I was saying that.
No, you weren't.
Come flying.
I was there.
You've been 10 toes down for Gaza.
And I just loved you for it.
I've loved you for it.
Thank you, Flora.
Where are you located?
So I'm in Utah.
I'm interesting because I am Chicana, Mexican-American.
I have a multi-ethnic background.
So my ancestors are from Africa.
They're indigenous Mexican.
They're European, Spanish, Italian, Swedish.
You know, and it's just like, I feel so lonely here sometimes, landlocked, because I'm not living on my ancestral land on all sides.
And this diaspora grief, learning the term diaspora grief has really helped me to, like, understand what's happening.
And I think something that you talk about a lot but not say the words is this genealogical consciousness, this ethical, moral way of behaving in the world with this genealogical consciousness, thinking about four generations before you, what were they doing, and four generations behind you, and then you're there in the middle.
So, and I just, I don't know, for Dia de Muertos, I set up an ofrenda every year, and I'm always like, do I put my European ancestors on there?
I don't have photographs of my black ancestors.
I only have documents that say, you know, mulato, or, and it's just like, as a multi-ethnic person, like, I am a combination of all these people.
I'm a combination of what, how America came to be, what it is, all lives in my body.
And sometimes I'm so proud of, like, the resiliency and the dignity, but then I'm also, like, so sorrowful of the really terrible part.
And with them trying to erase the real American history, I encourage, I'm a family history consultant, so I encourage everyone, learn your family history, share it, so that they can't, they can take away our history books, but they can't take our family, our history that lives in our body.
Can you talk to me about diaspora grief?
I've never heard that term.
Yeah, so diaspora is the people who live outside of their native country, like, wherever your DNA, whatever comes from, you live outside of your country.
And then this grief, it was actually coined by these amazing Asian American professors in California.
I'm trying to remember, they wrote a book called Racial Melancholia, and that book blew my mind.
Like, there were so many times when I was reading it, and I had to throw it across the room because it spoke so much truth that it scared me.
Like, I was like, ah!
And this, like, racial melancholia, this diaspora grief of, like, not being connected to your roots, and I don't think many people understand what colonization and enslavement did to us disconnecting us, or even immigration disconnecting us from our roots.
And there's a certain pain that goes with that, that we don't talk about, that we didn't have a name for.
And these Asian American professors, they were able to say, diaspora grief, racial melancholia.
And it is, anyway, I'm so excited to read your book, because this is where my heart lives, and more people talking about what our ancestors think of us, but also becoming new ancestors, and being the one that, like, I mean, that's how I feel about Gaza right now.
Like, I want my descendants to look back and see that I tried.
I really tried.
So, um, the book is the transcription of a one-woman show that I wrote, um, and I do a piece on, you know, being radicalized by Palestine.
And when I was performing this, you know, just off the top of my head, it was one thing, but once I sat down to, like, actually write, um, it took on, like, an even deeper kind of search.
And the, the point that I'm making is that when I started writing about the radicalization, like, my radicalization through Palestine, like, I felt like I was writing a record, you know?
Like, I felt like I was, like, writing it and a record that wasn't just my own, because I know so many of us, and I know that we have a grief about this, that it took this long.
I know that there's a grief that's very, that I, that I very deeply possess around the fact that, um, it's other people suffering that, that had to awaken me, you know?
Like, it feels, like, selfish, um, and, but it doesn't change the reality.
Uh, I just try to make sure that I'm being conscious around, you know, what that connectivity is.
And, and I, and it makes me also say that, like, that's also why, like, what you're saying about, like, being, like, we have to continue to be uncovering of our histories and not allowing erasure, because that does awaken.
Like, like, that, like, that's why they don't want people in the United States to know about the history of the United States, because your empathy gets awakened.
And once your empathy is awakened, you know, it's like, um, it's like energy tentacles that, like, you know, reach out to the world to be like, well, what's going on over here?
What's going on over here?
What's going on over here, you know?
And, and I feel like what you are experiencing is, like, you are the, you're, like, a being that's made up of so many different experiences.
And it's, like, all in one body.
And we're in this time of awakening that is just overwhelming that I feel like our parents and our grandparents didn't go through.
No, no.
And so there's, there's no leader.
That's why I feel like you hold that matriarch position, I think, for so many of us, because we are looking for, like, we, our parents, our grandparents, they didn't talk about this stuff.
They didn't, they didn't have words for it.
They didn't acknowledge it.
And just to, like, have someone that is leading out with authenticity, because that's another thing our family history does for us, is it gives us authenticity.
And it also prevents us from being hypocrites, where your ancestors were immigrants, you know?
And I, I'm a visual artist.
I'm an oil painter.
Okay.
And I've painted about these feelings, this racial melancholia, this diaspora grief.
Um, and since I'm talking to you, please let me do a painting for you, like, I can send you, I can send you samples of my work.
It's kind of like a family tree done in the style of Frida Kahlo, because she would, she experienced a lot of this questioning being, you know, her dad was German, her mom was indigenous Mexican, and just like those same questions that I've had.
And so, I would, I would love to do that for you.
What's your, um, hold on, let me write so I can follow you, so you can.
Flora familiar.
Flora familiar, or Flora familiar, whatever.
No, I like familiar.
Flora familiar.
Yeah.
Um.
Frida, Frida's up here somewhere.
Frida is up here somewhere.
Frida's always close by.
So, fun fact, doing my family history work, I found out that my ancestors lived, like, a block from Casa Azul, where her house is, and San Ange.
So, I don't know if they knew her or not, but I was like, I bet they knew of her, because how would you not know of her?
I mean, she was, you know.
Larger than life, yeah.
Yeah.
But I remember being a little girl in all-white class in elementary school, and they showed her picture, and she had her unibrow.
I had a unibrow, and everyone was like, ew, she's so gross, look at her unibrow, and just being like, that's me.
I see myself in art, and, like, that's my biggest thing as an artist, and I don't know what my ancestors would think of me.
Some would probably think I'm an abomination as a multiracial person.
What do you think they think about where we are?
I think this cycle has happened before.
When Cortez landed in Veracruz, where my family's from, I think they've seen it before.
When my African ancestors were taken from Cameroon to the port of Veracruz to work on the coffee plantations, like, I think they've seen this before.
And so I am reaching, like, a lot of my paintings show these, like, ribbons, trying to, like, latch onto them, to reach out and grab them, and whisper to me, teach me how you lived through this.
How am I here today?
Because you did live through this somehow.
And I know that, I know that we can, too.
We can, too.
We're going to be honest, and we're going to live with integrity, and we're going to speak up when we need to, and we're going to have courage, even though we're afraid.
Yep.
You got it.
Anyway, oh, honor.
Such an honor to speak with you.
It's been lovely speaking with you.
I learned.
I laughed.
And I can't wait to see your art.
I can't wait to paint it for you.
Like, please, please get in touch with me so I can.
It would be such an honor of my life.
Please.
I will.
Thank you so much for that familiar.
And keep your head up there in Utah.
Go out and look at the mountains when these white people be driving you crazy, because I know they do.
I know they do.
Have a good night.
You guys, we are so lucky to have this community.
And so this is what I want to be doing for the next month.
So I want you to think about who your ancestors are so that when we do these, you can request to come up and talk about what would your ancestors say about where we are, about where you are.
What would you say to your ancestors if you had the opportunity to speak with them, if you could connect with them?
I am such a deep believer that everything that we need to really actually eventually smote out the wickedness that has continued to be able to flourish on this planet is really attached to the planet itself.
And that's where our ancestors were attached.
So I encourage all of you all to really think about that.
Think about your ancestors.
And if you don't have any idea who your ancestors are, try to figure out who they could be.
If you're adopted, imagine, imagine, even, even the sky is the limit.
Who would you want your ancestors to be?
Let your, your love and your vision for where you came from and where we're going have no limits, have no limits.
I want to remind everyone to sign up for my newsletter so that you can get the link to get your tickets to the live stream performance of What Would the Ancestors Say, my one woman show, which is going to be released as a self-published work on November 8th.
And I hope that you will support my book.
I hope you will support my performance.
And when I come to a city near you, I hope that you can come and get your book signed.
So I hope to see you all soon over this next month as we continue to ask ourselves, what would your ancestors say?
Everyone have a great evening and let's keep our thoughts and hearts lifted for everyone out there who is being oppressed and for all the fighters who are fighting that oppression.
Have a good night.